Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
I'm thrilled to be here.
أنا متحمس بوجودي هنا.
I'm going to talk about a new, old material
سأقوم بالحديث حول مادة جديدة
that still continues to amaze us,
لا تزال تواصل إدهاشنا،
and that might impact the way we think
وقد تؤثر على طريقة تفكيرنا
about material science, high technology --
حول علم المواد، التكنولوجيا الفائقة --
and maybe, along the way,
وربما، على طول الطريق،
also do some stuff for medicine and for global health and help reforestation.
القيام ببعض الأمور للطب والصحة العامة وإعادة التشجير كذلك.
So that's kind of a bold statement.
إذن هذا نوع من الكلام الجريء.
I'll tell you a little bit more.
سأخبركم أكثر قليلا.
This material actually has some traits that make it seem almost too good to be true.
هذه المادة فعلا تتوفر على بعض الصفات تجعلها تبدو تقريبا في غاية الجودة حتى تكون صحيحة.
It's sustainable; it's a sustainable material
إنها مستدامة، إنها مادة مستدامة
that is processed all in water and at room temperature --
تتم معالجتها كلية في الماء وفي درجة حرارة الغرفة --
and is biodegradable with a clock,
وهي تتحلل بمؤقت،
so you can watch it dissolve instantaneously in a glass of water
وبالتالي يمكن مشاهدتها تتحلل لحظيا في كأس من الماء
or have it stable for years.
أو جعلها ثابتة لسنوات.
It's edible; it's implantable in the human body
إنها صالحة للأكل، قابلة للزرع في الجسم البشري
without causing any immune response.
بدون أن تسبب أي ردود فعل مناعية.
It actually gets reintegrated in the body.
يتم في الواقع إدماجها في الجسم.
And it's technological,
وهي تكنولوجية،
so it can do things like microelectronics,
وبالتالي يمكن أن تقوم بمثل ما تقوم به الإلكترونيات الدقيقة،
and maybe photonics do.
أو ربما الضوئيات.
And the material
والمادة
looks something like this.
تبدو هكذا.
In fact, this material you see is clear and transparent.
في الواقع، هذه المادة التي ترون واضحة وشفافة.
The components of this material are just water and protein.
مركبات هذه المادة هي فقط الماء والبروتين.
So this material is silk.
إذن هذه المادة هي الحرير.
So it's kind of different
حسنا إنها مختلفة نوعا ما
from what we're used to thinking about silk.
عما نعتبره حريرا.
So the question is, how do you reinvent something
إذن السؤال هو، كيف تعيد اختراع شيء
that has been around for five millennia?
متواجد منذ خمسة آلاف سنة؟
The process of discovery, generally, is inspired by nature.
عملية الإكتشاف، عموما، تلهمها الطبيعة.
And so we marvel at silk worms --
وهكذا تعجبنا من دود الحرير --
the silk worm you see here spinning its fiber.
دود الحرير ترونها هنا تغزل ليفها.
The silk worm does a remarkable thing:
دودة الحرير تقوم بأمر رائع:
it uses these two ingredients, protein and water,
تستخدم هذين المكونين الإثنين، البروتين والماء،
that are in its gland,
والموجودين في غدتها،
to make a material that is exceptionally tough for protection --
لإنتاج مادة إستثنائية الصلابة للحماية --
so comparable to technical fibers
إذن بالمقارنة مع الألياف التقنية
like Kevlar.
مثل كيفلر.
And so in the reverse engineering process
وهكذا في عملية الهندسة المعكوسة
that we know about,
التي نعرفها،
and that we're familiar with,
والتي ألفناها،
for the textile industry,
في صناعة النسيج،
the textile industry goes and unwinds the cocoon
صناعة النسيج تقوم بفك الشرنقة
and then weaves glamorous things.
وتنسج أمورا باهرة.
We want to know how you go from water and protein
نريد أن نعرف كيف تنتقل من الماء والبروتين
to this liquid Kevlar, to this natural Kevlar.
إلى كيلفر سائل، إلى هذا الكيلفر الطبيعي.
So the insight
لذا فالتبصر
is how do you actually reverse engineer this
هو كيف نقوم في الواقع بهندسة معكوسة على هذا
and go from cocoon to gland
والإنطلاق من الشرنقة إلى الغدة
and get water and protein that is your starting material.
والحصول على الماء والبروتين والذي هو المادة الأولية.
And this is an insight
وهذا تبصر
that came, about two decades ago,
ظهر قبل حوالي عقدين من الزمان
from a person that I'm very fortunate to work with,
من طرف شخص أنا محظوظ بالعمل معه،
David Kaplan.
ديفيد كابلان.
And so we get this starting material.
وهكذا نحصل على هذه المادة الأولية.
And so this starting material is back to the basic building block.
وهكذا ترجع المادة الأولية إلى لبنة البناء الأساسية.
And then we use this to do a variety of things --
ثم نستخدم هذه للقيام بأمور مختلفة --
like, for example, this film.
مثل الفيلم على سبيل المثال.
And we take advantage of something that is very simple.
ونستغل شيئا في غاية البساطة.
The recipe to make those films
وصفة إنتاج هذه الأفلام
is to take advantage of the fact
لاستغلال حقيقة
that proteins are extremely smart at what they do.
أن البروتينات هي في غاية الذكاء فيما تقوم به.
They find their way to self-assemble.
تجد طريقها للتجمع الذاتي.
So the recipe is simple: you take the silk solution, you pour it,
وهكذا فإن الوصفة بسيطة: تأخذ محلول الحرير، تصبه،
and you wait for the protein to self-assemble.
ثم تنتظر البروتينات لتتجمع ذاتيا.
And then you detach the protein and you get this film,
وثم تفصل البروتين لتحصل على هذا الفيلم،
as the proteins find each other as the water evaporates.
أثناء إيجاد البروتينات لبعضها البعض وهي تتبخر.
But I mentioned that the film is also technological.
لكن ذكرت أن الفيلم هو كذلك تقني.
And so what does that mean?
إذن ماذا يعني ذلك؟
It means that you can interface it
يعني أنه يمكن استخدامه كوسيط
with some of the things that are typical of technology,
مع بعض الأشياء التي التكنولوجية قياسيا،
like microelectronics and nanoscale technology.
مثل الإلكترونيات الدقيقة والتكنولوجيا على المستوى النانوي.
And the image of the DVD here
وصورة الDVD هنا
is just to illustrate a point
هي فقط لإيضاح فكرة
that silk follows very subtle topographies of the surface,
أن الحرير يتبع الطوبوغرافيات البالغة الرقة للسطح،
which means that it can replicate features on the nanoscale.
ما يعني أنه يمكن أن يستنسخ خواص على المستوى النانوي.
So it would be able to replicate the information
إذن سيكون قادرا على استنساخ المعلومات
that is on the DVD.
الموجودة على ال DVD.
And we can store information that's film with water and protein.
ويمكن أن نحفظ معلومات، ذاك هو الفيلم بالماء والبروتين.
So we tried something out, and we wrote a message in a piece of silk,
وبالتالي حاولنا أمرا، وكتبنا رسالة على قطعة من الحرير،
which is right here, and the message is over there.
والتي توجد هنا، والرسالة هناك.
And much like in the DVD, you can read it out optically.
وتماما مثل الDVD، يمكن أن تقرأ بصريا.
And this requires a stable hand,
وهذا يتطلب يدا ثابتة،
so this is why I decided to do it onstage in front of a thousand people.
ولهذا قررت أن أقوم بالأمر على الخشبة أمام ألف شخص.
So let me see.
إذن دعوني أر.
So as you see the film go in transparently through there,
لذا كما ترون الفيلم يمر بشفافية خلال هذا،
and then ...
ثم ..
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And the most remarkable feat
والخاصية الأكثر بروزا
is that my hand actually stayed still long enough to do that.
هي أن يدي بقيت بالفعل ثابتة بما فيه الكفاية للقيام بذلك.
So once you have these attributes
وبالتالي بمجرد الحصول على هذه السمات
of this material,
للمادة،
then you can do a lot of things.
حينها يمكن القيام بأمور كثيرة.
It's actually not limited to films.
إنها في الواقع غير محدودة بالأفلام.
And so the material can assume a lot of formats.
وبالتالي فالمادة يمكنها اتخاذ الكثير من الأشكال.
And then you go a little crazy, and so you do various optical components
ويمكن الذهاب بحماس أكثر، والقيام بمختلف المركبات البصرية
or you do microprism arrays,
أو مصفوفة موشور مجهري،
like the reflective tape that you have on your running shoes.
مثل الشريط العاكس الذي يوجد في أحذية الركض.
Or you can do beautiful things
أو يمكن القيام بأمور جميلة
that, if the camera can capture, you can make.
بحيث، إن كان بإمكان الكاميرا الإلتقاط، يمكن إنجاز.
You can add a third dimensionality to the film.
يمكن إضافة بعدية ثالثة للفيلم.
And if the angle is right,
وإن كانت الزاوية مناسبة،
you can actually see a hologram appear in this film of silk.
يمكن بالفعل رؤية هولوغرام يظهر على فلم الحرير هذا.
But you can do other things.
لكن يمكن القيام بأمور أخرى.
You can imagine that then maybe you can use a pure protein to guide light,
يمكنكم تخيل أنه ربما آنذاك يمكن استخدام بروتين خالص لإرشاد الضوء،
and so we've made optical fibers.
وهكذا فقد صنعنا أليافا ضوئية.
But silk is versatile and it goes beyond optics.
لكن الحرير متنوع ويذهب إلى ما وراء البصريات.
And you can think of different formats.
ويمكنكم التفكير في مختلف الأشكال.
So for instance, if you're afraid of going to the doctor and getting stuck with a needle,
إذن على سبيل المثال، إن كنتم تخافون من الذهاب إلى الطبيب وأن يتم حقنكم بإبرة،
we do microneedle arrays.
نعد مصفوفات إبرة مجهرية.
What you see there on the screen is a human hair
ما ترونه هناك على الشاشة هو شعرة بشرية
superimposed on the needle that's made of silk --
مركبة فوق الإبرة المصنوعة من الحرير --
just to give you a sense of size.
فقط لإعطائكم فكرة عن الحجم.
You can do bigger things.
يمكن القيام بأمور أكبر.
You can do gears and nuts and bolts --
يمكن صناعة تروس وصمولة ومسامير لولبية --
that you can buy at Whole Foods.
والتي يمكنكم شراؤها من محلات Whole Foods.
And the gears work in water as well.
والتروس تعمل في ماء كذلك.
So you think of alternative mechanical parts.
إذن نفكر في قطع ميكانيكية بديلة.
And maybe you can use that liquid Kevlar if you need something strong
وربما يمكن إستخدام ذاك الكيلفر السائل إن احتجتم إلى شيء أقوى
to replace peripheral veins, for example,
لتعويض الأوردة الطيفية،
or maybe an entire bone.
أو ربما عظمة بأكملها.
And so you have here a little example
إذن هنا ترون مثالا صغيرا
of a small skull --
لجمجة صغيرة --
what we call mini Yorick.
التي نسميها يوريك مصغر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But you can do things like cups, for example,
لكن يمكن إنتاج أشياء مثل أكواب، مثلا،
and so, if you add a little bit of gold, if you add a little bit of semiconductors
وهكذا، إن أضفتم القليل من الذهب، إن أضفتم القليل من المركبات الفائقة الموصلية
you could do sensors that stick on the surfaces of foods.
يمكن صناعة كواشف تلصق على سطح الأغذية.
You can do electronic pieces
يمكن إنتاج قطع إلكترونية
that fold and wrap.
تطوى وتلف.
Or if you're fashion forward, some silk LED tattoos.
أو إن كنتم تواقين للموضة، بعض الوشوم من الصمام المتألق الحرير.
So there's versatility, as you see,
وبالتالي هناك طلاقة، كما ترون،
in the material formats,
في أشكال المادة،
that you can do with silk.
التي يمكن أن تصنع من الحرير.
But there are still some unique traits.
لكن لا تزال هناك بعض الصفات المنفردة.
I mean, why would you want to do all these things for real?
أقصد، لماذا قد نود القيام بهذه الأمور كلها حقيقة؟
I mentioned it briefly at the beginning;
ذكرته باختصار في البدء؛
the protein is biodegradable and biocompatible.
البروتينات تتحلل أحيائيا ومتوافقة أحيائيا.
And you see here a picture of a tissue section.
وترون هنا صورة لمقطع نسيجي.
And so what does that mean, that it's biodegradable and biocompatible?
وبالتالي ما يعنيه ذلك، أنه يتحلل أحيائا ومتوافق أحيائيا؟
You can implant it in the body without needing to retrieve what is implanted.
يمكن زرعها في الجسم دون الحاجة إلى انتزاع المزروع.
Which means that all the devices that you've seen before and all the formats,
ما يعني أن كل الأجهزة التي رأيتم من قبل وكل الأشكال،
in principle, can be implanted and disappear.
يمكن مبدئيا، زرعها فتختفي.
And what you see there in that tissue section,
وما ترونه هناك في مقطع النسيج،
in fact, is you see that reflector tape.
هو، في الحقيقة، ترون ذلك الشريط العاكس.
So, much like you're seen at night by a car,
إذن، ما يشبه إلى حد كبير ما ترونه ليلا من السيارة،
then the idea is that you can see, if you illuminate tissue,
فالفكرة هي انه يمكن رؤية، إن أضأتم النسيج،
you can see deeper parts of tissue
يمكن رؤية أجزاء أعمق من النسيج
because there is that reflective tape there that is made out of silk.
لأنه يوجد فيه ذلك الشريط العاكس المصنوع من الحرير.
And you see there, it gets reintegrated in tissue.
وترون هناك، يتم إدماجها في النسيج.
And reintegration in the human body
ثم إدماجها في الجسم البشري
is not the only thing,
ليس الأمر الوحيد.
but reintegration in the environment is important.
لكن الإندماج مع البيئة مهم.
So you have a clock, you have protein,
وبالتالي لدينا ساعة، ولدينا بروتين،
and now a silk cup like this
والآن أكواب حرير مثل هذه
can be thrown away without guilt --
يمكن أن ترمى دون الإحساس بالذنب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
unlike the polystyrene cups
على خلاف أكواب البوليسترين
that unfortunately fill our landfills everyday.
والتي تملأ مطارح النفايات يوميا للأسف.
It's edible,
هي صالحة للأكل،
so you can do smart packaging around food
وبالتالي يمكن تغليف الطعام بغلاف ذكي
that you can cook with the food.
يمكن طبخه مع الطعام.
It doesn't taste good,
طعمه ليسا جيدا،
so I'm going to need some help with that.
لذلك سأحتاج بعض المساعدة في هذا.
But probably the most remarkable thing is that it comes full circle.
لكن الأمر الأكثر بروزا على الأرجح هو أنه يأتي في دائرة كاملة.
Silk, during its self-assembly process,
الحرير، وأثناء عملية تجمعه الذاتي،
acts like a cocoon for biological matter.
يعمل مثل شرنقة بمادة حيوية.
And so if you change the recipe,
وبالتالي حين تغير الوصفة،
and you add things when you pour --
وتضيف أشياء حين تصب --
so you add things to your liquid silk solution --
إذن تضيف أشياء إلى محلول الحرير السائل --
where these things are enzymes
بحيث تكون هذه الأشياء أنزيمات
or antibodies or vaccines,
أو مضادات أجسام أو حقن،
the self-assembly process
عملية التجمع الذاتي
preserves the biological function of these dopants.
تقي الوظيفة البيولوجية لهذه الشوائب.
So it makes the materials environmentally active
وبالتالي تجعل المادة فاعلة بيئيا
and interactive.
وتفاعلية.
So that screw that you thought about beforehand
وبالتالي ذلك البرغي الذي فكرتم فيه سلفا
can actually be used
يمكن في الواقع استعماله
to screw a bone together -- a fractured bone together --
لربط عظمة مع بعضها البعض -- عظمة مكسرة مع بعضها البعض --
and deliver drugs at the same,
وإيصال العقاقير في نفسها،
while your bone is healing, for example.
بينما تشفى العظمة، على سبيل المثال.
Or you could put drugs in your wallet and not in your fridge.
أو يمكنكم وضع الأدوية في محفظة نقودكم بدل الثلاجة.
So we've made a silk card
فقد صنعنا بطاقة حرير
with penicillin in it.
ببنسيلين داخلها.
And we stored penicillin at 60 degrees C,
وقمنا بحفظ البنسلين في 60 درجة مئوية،
so 140 degrees Fahrenheit,
أي 140 درجة فهرنهايت،
for two months without loss of efficacy of the penicillin.
لمدة شهرين دون فقدان فعالية البنسلين.
And so that could be ---
وبالتالي هذا قد يكون ---
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
that could be potentially a good alternative
يحتمل أن يكون بديلا جيدا
to solar powered refrigerated camels. (Laughter)
لثلاجات الجمال التي تعمل بالشمس.
And of course, there's no use in storage if you can't use [it].
وبالطبع، ليس هناك نفع للتخزين إن لم نستطع استخدامه.
And so there is this other unique material trait
وبالتالي هناك خاصية أخرى فريدة للمادة
that these materials have, that they're programmably degradable.
وهي أن هذه المواد تتوفر على، أنها يمكن برمجة تحللها.
And so what you see there is the difference.
وبالتالي ما ترونه هناك هو الفرق.
In the top, you have a film that has been programmed not to degrade,
في الأعلى، لدينا فيلم تمت برمجته بحيث لا يتحلل،
and in the bottom, a film that has been programmed to degrade in water.
وفي الأسفل، فيلم تمت برمجته حتى يتحلل في الماء.
And what you see is that the film on the bottom
وما ترونه هو أن الفيلم في الأسفل
releases what is inside it.
يطلق ما بداخله.
So it allows for the recovery of what we've stored before.
وبالتالي يسمح باسترجاع ما تم تخزينه فيه من قبل.
And so this allows for a controlled delivery of drugs
وهكذا يسمح بإيصال متحكم للأدوية
and for reintegration in the environment
واندماج مع البيئة
in all of these formats that you've seen.
في كل تلك الأشكال التي رأيتم.
So the thread of discovery that we have really is a thread.
وبالتالي الخيط الناظم للإكتشاف الذي لدينا هو في الواقع خيط ناظم.
We're impassioned with this idea that whatever you want to do,
نحن متحمسون لفكرة أنه أي شيء تريد القيام به،
whether you want to replace a vein or a bone,
سواء أردت تعويض وريد أو عظم،
or maybe be more sustainable in microelectronics,
أو ربما إلكترونيات مجهرية أكثر استدامة،
perhaps drink a coffee in a cup
ربما شرب القهوة في كوب
and throw it away without guilt,
ثم رميه دون الشعور بالذنب،
maybe carry your drugs in your pocket,
ربما حمل الأدوية في الجيب،
deliver them inside your body
إيصالها إلى داخل الجسم
or deliver them across the desert,
أو عبر الصحراء،
the answer may be in a thread of silk.
الجواب قد يكون في خيط الحرير.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)